<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>My Awesome Blog: Posts tagged 'projects'</title>
  <description>My Awesome Blog: Posts tagged 'projects'</description>
  <link>https://cwang.me/tags/projects.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 20:52:54 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 20:52:54 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>Stat 230 Problem: Professor X ' s evil grading scheme</title>
   <link>https://cwang.me/blog/2015/05/12/stat-230-problem-professor-x-s-evil-grading-scheme/?utm_source=projects&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid>urn:https-cwang-me:-blog-2015-05-12-stat-230-problem-professor-x-s-evil-grading-scheme</guid>
   <pubDate>Tue, 12 May 2015 20:52:54 UT</pubDate>
   <description>&lt;html&gt;
&lt;script src="http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_SVG.js" type="text/javascript"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h1&gt;&lt;a name="(part._)"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found a really interesting problem in my STAT 230 course notes. Problem 2.8 on page 14 involves a cheeky and/or evil professor who decides to play a game with two of his students to determine their respective grades in STAT 230. The game is essentially to guess the professor&amp;rsquo;s number, and to have a better guess than the other person. I found the problem fairly interesting, and although I lacked the theoretical knowledge to be able to solve it and prove that I had found an optimal solution, I knew I could code up a simulation and have fun doing it. &lt;a href="http://cwang.me/Stats"&gt;Here is what I came up with&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name="(part._.The_problem)"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The problem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic"&gt;Anonymous professor X has an integer \((1 \leq m \leq 9)\) in mind and asks two students, Allan and Beth to pick numbers between 1 and 9. Whichever is closer to m gets 90% and the other 80% in STAT 230. If they are equally close, they both get 85%. If the professor&amp;#8217;s number and that of Allan are chosen purely at random and Allan announces his number out loud, describe a sample space and a strategy which leads Beth to the highest possible mark.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;&lt;a name="(part._.Strategies)"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Strategies&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The simulation repeats the game a few thousand times to determine the expected value of Beth&amp;rsquo;s mark. The question asks for us to find a strategy for picking a number, given Allan&amp;rsquo;s number, that maximizes Beth&amp;rsquo;s mark. Trivially, if Beth only wanted to avoid the worst case, then picking the same number as Allan every time would guarantee this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One possible strategy is given by&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\[f(n) = \left\{
     \begin{array}{lr}
       n + 1 &amp;amp; : n &amp;lt; 5 \\
       n     &amp;amp; : n = 5 \\
       n - 1 &amp;amp; : n &amp;gt; 5
     \end{array}
  \right.\]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="SIntrapara"&gt;with the code &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="SIntrapara"&gt;
 &lt;pre class="brush: js"&gt;if (n &amp;lt; 5) return n + 1; if (n &amp;gt; 5) return n - 1; return n;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can run it yourself a few times and see that it&amp;rsquo;s a little better than randomly picking. Plus the strategy is more feasible than picking randomly&amp;ndash;it&amp;rsquo;s hard to pick random numbers in your head, after all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What are some of your strategies for maximizing Beth&amp;rsquo;s mark?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>