<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?> 
<rss version="2.0">
 <channel>
  <title>My Awesome Blog: Posts tagged 'tutorials'</title>
  <description>My Awesome Blog: Posts tagged 'tutorials'</description>
  <link>https://cwang.me/tags/tutorials.html</link>
  <lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 19:25:06 UT</lastBuildDate>
  <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 19:25:06 UT</pubDate>
  <ttl>1800</ttl>
  <item>
   <title>My CS 246/136 workflow, or how to fork a git repository</title>
   <link>https://cwang.me/blog/2015/05/08/my-cs-246-136-workflow-or-how-to-fork-a-git-repository/?utm_source=tutorials&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid>urn:https-cwang-me:-blog-2015-05-08-my-cs-246-136-workflow-or-how-to-fork-a-git-repository</guid>
   <pubDate>Fri, 08 May 2015 19:25:06 UT</pubDate>
   <description>&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The instructions for CS 246 are quite simple: clone the course repository so that you have your own local copy, and then pull from it periodically while committing to it for your own assignments. This is fine, but then you have to resort to rsync or scp to keep files synchronized between the linux.student.cs servers and your own computer; realistically, not everyone wants to ssh in and use vim. These instructions will show you how to have your own local repository that you can sync with a remote one using only git, which I find quite convenient. I used this for CS 136 and I&amp;rsquo;m using it now for CS 246.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The goal here is to have a central repository of sorts, just for synchronization. It replicates GitHub&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;fork&amp;rdquo; functionality by giving you your own remote repository that you can push to. This is desirable because syncing files becomes a simple git pull/git push (and maybe a merge or two), and the student environment servers have good &lt;a href="http://math.uwaterloo.ca/math-faculty-computing-facility/recover-files"&gt;backups&lt;/a&gt; and uptime&amp;mdash;they likely won&amp;rsquo;t fail completely, unlike your cheap laptop. Also, if the student environment goes down, it&amp;rsquo;s not your responsibility to fix it (ie. courses will make accommodations for it), unlike your laptop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First set up a bare clone of the repository.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: bash"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;cd ~/cs246
git clone --bare https://git.uwaterloo.ca/cs246/1155.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then clone it again for your own working copy of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: bash"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone 1155.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On your own computer, clone using ssh from your own bare repository. Don&amp;rsquo;t forget to clone from the bare repository; note that by convention bare repositories are appended with .git.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: bash"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git clone ssh://userid@linux.student.cs.uwaterloo.ca/~/cs246/1155.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then in both systems, you need to add an &amp;ldquo;upstream&amp;rdquo; URL so that you can fetch and pull from the offical course repository. The name doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be upstream, but remember to use the correct name in the other commands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: bash"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git remote add upstream https://git.uwaterloo.ca/cs246/1155.git&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now to &amp;ldquo;pull from upstream&amp;rdquo; you need to first fetch, and then merge. This is what you do instead of git pull if you want to update from the course repository to get new assignments and handouts. CS 246 should stay on the master branch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class="brush: bash"&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;git fetch upstream
git merge upstream/master&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To synchronize files between your computer and the linux.student.cs servers, use git pull/push. For example, you could be working on assignment and finish part of it in one night. You commit and push. Then the next day you can go to a computer lab, log in, and pull to resume work from where you left off. Of course, this workflow is also compatible with other workflows such as the &lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/git/tutorials/comparing-workflows/feature-branch-workflow"&gt;feature branch workflow&lt;/a&gt;, but it might be overkill for assignments.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</description></item>
  <item>
   <title>How to access Seashell files</title>
   <link>https://cwang.me/blog/2015/03/24/how-to-access-seashell-files/?utm_source=tutorials&amp;utm_medium=RSS</link>
   <guid>urn:https-cwang-me:-blog-2015-03-24-how-to-access-seashell-files</guid>
   <pubDate>Tue, 24 Mar 2015 20:08:55 UT</pubDate>
   <description>&lt;html&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all love Seashell, because the only course-sanctioned alternative would be to use RunC inside VirtualBox. But sometimes, the CSCF servers buckle under our load, and then Seashell becomes slow or inaccessible at times. Or maybe, since you worked hard on all your assignments, you just want to keep a copy of your them. Here&amp;rsquo;s how to get your files from Seashell, even if Seashell is down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can also delete the object (.o) files from Seashell this way, because you currently can&amp;rsquo;t do that through Seashell itself. You might need this for A10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="windows-users"&gt;Windows Users&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Navigate to This PC / My Computer.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Click &amp;ldquo;Map Network Drive&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Pick any drive you want, maybe W: for Waterloo, and for Folder, enter &lt;code&gt;\\smb-files.student.cs.uwaterloo.ca\USERID&lt;/code&gt; where USERID is your Quest/WatIAM/whatever username.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Enter &lt;code&gt;\CS-TEACHING\USERID&lt;/code&gt; as the username. If you&amp;rsquo;ve used Seashell before, enter your standard Waterloo password here. If this doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, &lt;a href="https://www.student.cs.uwaterloo.ca/password/"&gt;reset your password&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Now enter your newly-added network drive. Optional: Show hidden files/folders by going to View &amp;gt; tick &amp;ldquo;Hidden items&amp;rdquo; from the menubar.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;If you didn&amp;rsquo;t want to show hidden files/folders, append &lt;code&gt;.seashell&lt;/code&gt; to the path in the location bar and press enter. Otherwise, enter the &lt;code&gt;.seashell&lt;/code&gt;folder. It will appear greyed out because it is a hidden folder.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;All your Seashell projects will be in the &lt;code&gt;projects&lt;/code&gt; folder. You can copy these files as you would for any other file in Windows. Don&amp;rsquo;t move/delete anything unless you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing, but copying is safe.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/img/pub/windows_network_drive_.png"&gt;&lt;img src="/img/pub/windows_network_drive_.png" alt="Screenshot of This PC / My Computer" style="width: 500px;" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;img src="/img/pub/windows_logon.png" alt="" /&gt; &lt;img src="/img/pub/windows_seashell_folder.png" alt="" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id="mac-users"&gt;Mac Users&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: these instructions work for the Mac Labs too, but you can skip step 6.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Open Finder.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;From the menu, Go -&amp;gt; Connect to Server&amp;hellip; (command-K)&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Enter &lt;code&gt;smb://smb-files.student.cs.uwaterloo.ca/USERID&lt;/code&gt; as the Server Address, where USERID is your Quest/WatIAM/whatever username.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Optional: Click the "+" icon to add it to favourites.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Click Connect.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Enter your username/password. If this doesn&amp;rsquo;t work, &lt;a href="https://www.student.cs.uwaterloo.ca/password/"&gt;reset your password&lt;/a&gt;. Note: after this step, it might be necessary to manually go into your user folder. Just scroll through and find it; the folder name is your username.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Navigate to the &lt;code&gt;.seashell&lt;/code&gt; hidden folder: Go &amp;gt; Go to Folder (Shift-Command-G), type &lt;code&gt;.seashell&lt;/code&gt;. Go.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;All your Seashell projects will be in the &lt;code&gt;projects&lt;/code&gt; folder. You can copy these files as you would for any other file. Don&amp;rsquo;t move/delete anything unless you know what you&amp;rsquo;re doing, but copying is safe.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;&lt;img src="/img/pub/Mac_smb_add.png" alt="" /&gt;
 &lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="figure"&gt;&lt;img src="/img/pub/Mac_finder_goto_seashell.png" alt="" /&gt;
 &lt;p class="caption"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h1 id="linux-users"&gt;Linux Users&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seashell files are all stored under &lt;code&gt;~/.seashell/projects/&lt;/code&gt; on &lt;code&gt;linux.student.cs.uwaterloo.ca&lt;/code&gt;. If you know how to mount SMB shares (I don&amp;rsquo;t), the address is &lt;code&gt;smb://smb-files.student.cs.uwaterloo.ca/USERID&lt;/code&gt; where USERID is your username. Or just mount the root and navigate to your directory. Or just scp and whatever.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>